Guide to the Draft and War Resistance Movement, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1966-1972 AIS.1968.18
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Draft and War Resistance Movement, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1966-1972
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Draft and War Resistance Movement (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1968.18
2.81 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
The records of the Pittsburgh draft and war resistance movement were collected between 1966-1972 and donated by University of Pittsburgh graduate student, David Morrison, coordinator of the Pittsburgh Draft Information Center which provided Conscientious Objector (C.O.) counseling service. Materials include books, brochures, calls to meetings, correspondence, court cases, legal briefs, manuscripts, miscellaneous mimeographed leaflets, pamphlets, publications and issues of local and national resistance newspapers relating to draft resisters and peace movements.
Scope and Content Notes
Graduate student, David R. Morrison, was active in the draft and war resistance movement at the University of Pittsburgh and coordinator of the Pittsburgh Draft Information Center which provided Conscientious Objector (C.O.) counseling service.
Materials include books, brochures, calls to meetings, correspondence, court cases, legal briefs, statements, manuscripts, miscellaneous mimeographed leaflets, pamphlets, publications and issues of local and national resistance newspapers relating to draft resisters and peace movements.
Series I consists of the correspondence, biographical information and manuscripts of David R. Morrison along with various official Statements of Non-Compliance with the Selective Service System. This series also contains a book that was based on a 1966 Pittsburgh study of the Selective Service System.
Series II and III contain information from various Pittsburgh area and national draft and war resistance groups. Series IV contains various local and national draft and war resistance movement publications, information regarding court cases and a draft information kit. Also contained in Series IV are handbills concerning civil disobedience, conscientious objection, (draft) resistance and protesting the Vietnam War.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by David Morrison in 1968 and 1983.
Previous Citation
Draft and War Resistance Movement Records, Pittsburgh, Pa., 1966-1972, AIS.1968.18, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Draft and War Resistance Movement, Pittsburgh, Pa., 1966-1972, ais 68:18, Archives of Industrial Society, University Library System, Hillman Library, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pa.
Conscientious objectors -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Draft resisters -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social action; Peace movements -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies, etc.; Politics; Political movements -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social conditions; Radicalism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social movements -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Underground press publications -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Underground press publications -- United Sates; Draft and War Resistance Movement (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Morrison, David R. -- Correspondence
- David R. Morrison Papers, I.
  - Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Setting up of the Phila. Draft Inf. Center, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Draft Counseling, The Unauthorized Practice of Law, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Biographical Information (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Legal brief in re Howard S. Gross, Jr., ca. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Manuscripts of Articles and Presentations (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum in response to the Dept. of Justice recommendations re Howard S. Gross, Jr., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Draft Counseling, ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Wormsley, Gary L., Selective Services A Changing America, Columbus, Charles E. Merritt, 1969. Comment on by DRM, ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Statements of Non-Compliance with the Selective Service System, (late 1960's) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Pittsburgh Draft and War Resistance Groups, II.
  - Pittsburgh Draft Information Center (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pittsburgh Draft Resistance (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pittsburgh Committee to End the War in Vietnam (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Peace and Freedom Center (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Resistance, Pittsburgh., Pa. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Pittsburgh Veterans for Peace (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - ECCO (Expression, Cogitation, Creation, Observation) University of Pittsburgh (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Peace and Social Action Committee, Pittsburgh., Pa. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pittsburgh Area Program Committee (American Friends Service Comm.) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pittsburgh Fellowship of Reconciliation (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Communist Party of Western Pa. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Pittsburgh Free University (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pittsburgh W.E.B. DuBois Club [EMPTY] (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pittsburgh Peace Coalition (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Western Pennsylvania Academic Council on Problems of War and Peace, Pgh., Pa. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Western Pennsylvania Students Conference for Peace Activities, Pgh., Pa. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Draft and War Resistance Groups, III.
  - Campus Draft Opposition, Berkeley, Calif. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Boston Draft Resistance Group (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - New England Committee for Non-Violent Action, Voluntown, Conn. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - New England Resistance (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Resistance, New York, New York (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Student Peace Union (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Prisoners Information and Support Service, Boston, Mass. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Religious Soc. of Friends in Am. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - War Resistors League, New York, New York (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Philadelphia Resistance (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Draft and War Resistance Movement Publications, IV.
  - Liberation, N.Y., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - The Conscientious Clavichord, Calif., Pa., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Bring the Troops Home Now, N.Y., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Medical Resistance Union (MRU) Newsletter, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - New England Resistance, Boston, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Peacemaker, Cincinnati, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 35-37)
  - Pittsburgh Peace and Freedom News, 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Reporter for Conscience' Sake, Wash., D.C., 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Resistance: Nat. Ed., Boston, National Newsletter, Cambridge, San Francisco, 1968; 1967-68; 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - The Resister, Philadelphia, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Support Newsletter, Cambridge, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Vietnam GI, Chicago, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Veterans Stars Stripes for Peace, Chicago, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - War Resistance League News, N.Y., 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Bond, the Servicemen's Newspaper, N.Y., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Win: Peace and Freedom Through Non-Violent Action, N.Y., 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
  - Win: Peace and Freedom Through Non-Violent Action, N.Y., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Draft Information, Court Cases, Manuscript, Leaflets, Brochures and Pamphlets, V.
  - Draft Info Kit (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - United States vs. John Mamear (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - United States vs. Robert Paul Nelkin (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Samuel P. Hays, The Anti-War Movement in Transition: The Shift to the Left, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Civil Disobedience (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Conscientious Objection (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Draft/draft resistance (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - Vietnam War -- Protest/Resistance (Box 5, Folder 1-5)